<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The forme of the agreement made at Strumsdorff Of the truce for twenty six yeares to come, concluded betwixt the high and mighty prince, the Kings Majesty of Poland, great Duke of Lettow, &amp;c. as also of the kingdome of Poland, and great dukedome of Lettow; on tbe [sic] one party. And the high and mighty princesse, the Queenes Maiestie, and kingdome of Sweden; on the other partie. Comprised in twenty foure articles.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc. Sweden, 1635 Sept. 2. English and Latin</title>
            <author>Poland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117909</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18486</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18486)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1010:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The forme of the agreement made at Strumsdorff Of the truce for twenty six yeares to come, concluded betwixt the high and mighty prince, the Kings Majesty of Poland, great Duke of Lettow, &amp;c. as also of the kingdome of Poland, and great dukedome of Lettow; on tbe [sic] one party. And the high and mighty princesse, the Queenes Maiestie, and kingdome of Sweden; on the other partie. Comprised in twenty foure articles.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc. Sweden, 1635 Sept. 2. English and Latin</title>
                  <author>Poland.</author>
                  <author>Sweden. Treaties, etc. Poland, 1635 Sept. 2. English and Latin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Nathaniel Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With additional title page: Formula Stumsdorfianorum pactorum de induciis XXVI. annorum ..</note>
                  <note>Dated on E3r: the second of September, old stile .. 1635.</note>
                  <note>Latin and English on facing pages.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>In at least one copy, "tter" of Butter's name in the English imprint has not printed (STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FORME <hi>Of the</hi> Agreement <hi>made at</hi> Strumſdorff. <hi>Of the</hi> Truce <hi>for twenty ſix yeares to come, concluded betwixt</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The High and Mighty <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>Kings Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> Great Duke of <hi>Lettow,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and Great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow;</hi> on the one Party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> The High and Mighty <hi>Princeſſe,</hi> the <hi>Queenes Maieſtie,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Sweden;</hi> on the other Partie.</p>
            <p>Compriſed in twenty foure Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed by</hi> Thomas Harper, <hi>for</hi> Nathaniel Butter, <hi>and</hi> Nicholas Bourne, <hi>1635.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FORMVLA Stumſdorfianorum pactorum de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciis XXVI. annorum inter Sereniſſ. <hi>Poloniae</hi> Regem, Magnum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Ducem <hi>Lithuaniae,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; Regnum Poloniae, Magnum Ducatum <hi>Lithuaniae;</hi> ab unâ</p>
            <p>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> Sereniſſ. Reginam, Regnumque <hi>Sueciae;</hi> ab altera parte ſancitis: XXIV. articulis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſa.</p>
            <p>LONDINI, Apud <hi>Thomam Harperum</hi> pro <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniele Butter</hi> &amp; <hi>Nicolao Bourn,</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ladiſlaus IV. Dei gratia Poloniae, Magnus Dux Lithuaniae, &amp;c. Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c. Dediſſe Nos Commiſſarios nostros plena poteſtate ac mandatis Jnſtructos ad Tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, (interveniente mediatione Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſsimorum Galliae &amp; Magnae Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniae Regum, aliorumque Principu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) de pace aut Jnauciis cum Sereniſsima Principe, ac Domina Chriſtina, Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, Gothorum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andolorumque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignata Reginâ, Magna Principe Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiae, &amp;c. conſanguinea nostra, &amp; Regno Sueciae. Qui congreſsi cum Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitacis eius, &amp; Regni Sueciae Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariis;
<pb facs="tcp:18486:4"/>ſequentia Pacta, (uti verbote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus infra ſunt expreſſa &amp; inſerta) ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, ſtatuerunt, ac concluſerunt.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ladſlaus</hi> the fourth, by the grace of <hi>God</hi> King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> great Duke of <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tow,</hi> &amp;c. Wee doe hereby ſignifie, &amp;c. That wee have given moſt full authority unto our <hi>Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> with ſufficient <hi>Mandates</hi> and <hi>Jnſtructions:</hi> to <hi>treate</hi> (the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the High and Mighty <hi>Princes</hi> the Kings of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of <hi>France;</hi> with ſome other <hi>Princes</hi> intervening) upon a <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of <hi>Armes,</hi> with the High and Mighty <hi>Princeſſe</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Chriſtina deſigned Queene</hi> of the <hi>Suedens, Goths,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andalls, Great Princeſſe</hi> of <hi>Finland,</hi> Our <hi>Coſin;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Who meeting with the <hi>Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:4"/>of her <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>Sweden:</hi> have agreed, ſet downe, and concluded upon theſe following <hi>Articles:</hi> as they are, word for word, here expreſſed and inſerted.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="treaty">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OS, Sereniſsimi ac Potentiſsimi Principis ac Domini, Dn. Vladiſlai IV. Dei Gratia Regis Poloniae, ac Magni Ducis Lithvaniae, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tque inclitae Repub. Polonae Commiſsarii: Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus Zadzik Epiſcopus Culmenſis &amp; Pomeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, Nominatus Cracovienſis, Dux Severienſis, Generalis Praepoſitus Miechovienſis, Supremus Regni Poloniae Cancellarius: Raphael Comes de Leſno, Palatinus Belzenſis, Rubieſſovienſis, &amp;c. Praefectus: Magnus Erneſtus Donnhoff Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus Pernavienſis; Derpatenſis, Oberpolienſis Praefectus: Remigius de Otok Zalesky Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendarius Regni: Iacobus â Sobiezin Sobiesky Inciſor Regni; Craſnoſtavienſis, Iavorovienſis Praefectus. Notum teſtatumque facimus Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quorum intereſt; quod cum induciae Sexen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ales inter Sereniſsimos ac Potentiſsimos Reges
<pb facs="tcp:18486:6"/>ac Regna Poloniae &amp; Sueciae eo inter alia fine Anno <hi>1629</hi> ſancitae eſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; ut interea vel de pace perpetua vel inductis longioribus interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente mediatione Sereniſsimorum ac Potentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimorum Galliae &amp; Angliae Regum aliorumque Principum, loco &amp; tempore, de quibus per ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſ. Electorem randeburgicum, &amp;c. Vnum ex iiſdem Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>toribus, inter Partes conventum eſſet, age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etur: Jnde poſt quam à ſua ſerenitate per ejuſdem Legatos Illuſtr. Principem Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum Marchionem Brandeburgicum, &amp; Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtres ac Magnificos Andream à Creutzen, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarium Ducalis Pruſsiae, Regentem &amp; Praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Provincialem; Iohannem Georgium à Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iarium Regentem &amp; Cancellarium: Bernhardum à Konigſeck Conſiliarium Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialem, Georgium à Rauſckeu Conſiliarium Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii, aulici &amp; Petrum Bergkmannum Conſilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, Secretioris Conſilii invitati Stumsdor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fium, cum Illuſtr. Sereniſsimae Regnique Sueciae Commiſſariis; Domino Petro Brabe Comite in Viſingsburg Lib. Barone in Rydholm &amp; Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm Regni Sueciae Senatore, Legifero Weſman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae Montanorum &amp; Dale-Carlorum; Hermanno Wrangelio Regni Sueciae Senatore &amp; Exercituu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:7"/>Campi-Mareſchallo Haereditario in Lergeholm, Sko Cloſter, Equite Aurato; Achatio Axelii, Regni Sueciae Senatore &amp; Legifero Nericiae, Haereditario in Coxholm, &amp;c Ioanne Oxenſtier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Axelii ſeren: Reginae Conſiliario ſecretiore, Lib Barone in Kimitho, Domino in Fiholm &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idoen: &amp; Ioanne Nicodemi ſereniſsimae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae ſecretario, &amp; ad Exercitum Pruſsicum Commiſſario Generali, Conveniſſemus: ac interventu inprimis ſereniſſ. &amp; Potentiſsimi Principis Domini, Domint Ludovici <hi>13.</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae &amp; Navarrae Reg is Chriſtianiſmi per Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſsimum Dominum Claudium de Meſmes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitem Anratum, Dominum de Avax, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitem Conſiſtorianum &amp;c. R M. per Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tren rionem extraordinarium Legatum; ac ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſ. &amp; potentiſſ. Principis Domini Domini Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli Magnae Britaniae, &amp;c. Regis, Fidei Defenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, per Illuſtriſſ. Dominum Georgium Douglaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium, Equitem Auratum, S. R. M. Legatum; nec non Celſorum ac Praepotentium D. D. Ordinum Belgii per Illuſtres &amp; Magnificos Legatos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos Rochum van den Honaert Primarius ſuprema Hollandiae, Zelandiae, Weſtphriſiaque Curia Conſiliarium, Andream Bicker Conſulem Civitat is Amſtelredamenſis, &amp; Ioachimum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreae in ſuprema Friſiae Curia Conſiliarium pacis
<pb facs="tcp:18486:8"/>
               <hi>Tractatum auſpicati eſſemus, ac diu multumque agitaſſemus; eo tandem divino Numine faven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te praedictiſque Illuſtriſsimis Legatis indefeſſam operam huic negotio impendentibus, rem dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus, ut cum praememòratis Sereniſsimae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae Regnique Sueciae Commiſſariis de Induciis admodum ſequentem convenimus, ſtatuerimus &amp; concluſerimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:9"/>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>SInt Iuduciae ex hoe die inter Sereniſſimum Principem &amp; Dominum, Dominum <hi>Vladiſlaum IV.</hi> Regem Poloniae, Magnum Ducem Lithvaniae, &amp;c. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num noſtrum clementiſſimum, Suae Majeſtatis ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores, Reges <hi>Poloniae</hi> Magnos Duces <hi>Lithvaniae,</hi> Regnumque <hi>Poloniae</hi> &amp; Magnum Ducatum <hi>Lithvaniae,</hi> ex unâ, &amp; inter Sereniſſimam Principiſſam &amp; Dominam, Dominam <hi>Chriſtianam, Svecorum, Gotthorum, Vanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo umqued</hi> ſignatam Reginam, Magnam Principiſſam <hi>Finlandiae,</hi> &amp;c. Suae Majeſtatis ſucceſſores, Reges <hi>Sveco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> Regnumque <hi>Sveciae,</hi> ex alterâ parte, annis ſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus viginti ſex à datâ praeſentium computando, uſque ad primam <hi>Iulii,</hi> ſtilo veteri Anno M.DC.LXI.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Sit omnium utrinque ante actorum amniſtia. Jmprimis Sac: Regia Majeſtas, ejuſque Succeſſores. Reges, Regnum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que <hi>Poloniae,</hi> &amp; Magni Ducatus <hi>Lithaviae</hi> abſtineant du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantibus induciis omni hoſtilitate, adverſus Reginam, Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numque <hi>Svecorum</hi> iiſque mediate vel immediatè ſubjectas Provincias, Caſtra, Civitates, ac Territoria, neque quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam perſe, vel per alios moliantur, aut tentent, tentarivè faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt in horum detrimentum aut praejudicium. Ad eundem modum Sereniſſima Regina ejuſque Succeſſores, Reges Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numque <hi>Sveciae</hi> abſtineant durantibus Jnduciis omni hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate adverſus Regem, Regnumque <hi>Poloniae,</hi> &amp; Magnum Duc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum <hi>Lithvania,</hi> iiſque mediatè vel immediatè ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas Provincias, Caſtra, Civitates ac Territoria, neque quecquam perſe vel per alios moliatur, tentent, tentarivè facrant, in horum detrimentum &amp; praejudicium.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:10"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Sereniſſimo Regi ae Reipub. <hi>Polonae,</hi> Sereniſſima Regina Regnumque <hi>Sveciae</hi> reddat cam partem <hi>Pruſſiae,</hi> quam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctenus occupatam poſſidet, ita tamen, ut <hi>Pillavia</hi> Electori <hi>Brandenburgico</hi> Duci in <hi>Pruſſia</hi> immediate reſtituatur; poſſidenda eojure, quo ante hoc bellum habuit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>In reſtituendis verò locis, hoc obſervetur: ut exhibitâ Commiſſariis <hi>Svevicis</hi> Regis <hi>Poloniae</hi> ratificatione, nec non interpoſit â Senatorum cautione, &amp; Commiſſariorum <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorum</hi> lege comitiali ad latus Regis à Rep. delegatorum, de tradenda primo quoque tempore Reip. ratificatione, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaeburgum</hi> cum Jnſulâ majori, <hi>Stuma, Brunsberga,</hi> ac <hi>Tolckemitum,</hi> cum eorum territorriis, deductis praeſdiis reddatur in manus Commiſſariorum Regis ac Regni <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae. Hauptium</hi> verò &amp; <hi>Iunckertreil</hi> praeſentibus utriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que partis deputatis ſolo aequentur, ſuis cuique fundis &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis relictis: &amp; exercitus utrinque abducantur intra id tempus, codem modo &amp; ordine, quo inter Generales utriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que partis convenerit. <hi>Elbingam</hi> verò cum priſtino ejus Territorio, atque inſulâ minori ac munimentis ibi exſtructis, nec non <hi>Pillaviam</hi> cum eâ parte <hi>Neringiae,</hi> quae eò ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat, retineat ſua Regia Majeſtas Regnumque <hi>Sveciae,</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec ratificatio Reip. <hi>Polonae</hi> ſubſecuta fuerit: quâ tradit â, illa quoque loca intra dies quatuordecim, deductis ſine dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Jncolarum praeſidiis reſtituat. Hoc obſervato, ut fortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia omnia <hi>Elbingae</hi> exſtructa, relinquantur omnia eo inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, in quo nunc ſunt, &amp; eâdem cuſtodiâ ut ante hoc bellu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:11"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Poſt reſtitutionem locorum omnium vectigalia in eum mox redigantur ſtatum, &amp; in illud ius, in quo erant ante hoc bellum, ſervatâ in omnibus aequalitate, uti antea fuit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acta, iudicata, ac decreta cujuſcunque fuerint inſtantiae, vel judicu, inſcriptiones, contractus, tranſactiones, aliaque omnia, quae ſtatui publico uti is fuit ante bellum, non dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, vel hiſcep ctis per expreſſum non ſunt reſervata, belli vel induciarum tempore, ſive Magiſtratuum authoritate, &amp; judicialiter geſta, firmum robur obtineant, aequè ac ſi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore rerum ſtatu omnia acta fuiſſent, nec ulla unquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimims &amp; Magiſtratuum mutatio interveniſſet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jn Livonia utraque pars, uti praeteritis ſexennalibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciis poſſedit, ita hiſce quoque poſſideat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:12"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex ac Reſp. Bolona receptas in fidem ſuam Civitates ac Territoria, eorumque Magiſtratus, Communitates; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, Jncolas &amp; ſubditos univerſos omni meliore modo indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, praeſt et, ac eâdem, quo olim, Clementia &amp; Grati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequatur, foveat ac tueatur: gaudeantque univerſi &amp; ſinguli poſſeſſionibus, juribus, Privilegiis, conſuetudinibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, ſuis, (tam generalibus ac communibus, quam ſpeciali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus) ſine exceptione, quibus ante hoc bellum gaviſi ſunt: praeſertim vero Civitas Elbingenſis in uſu ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gills terrarum Pruſſiae, &amp; conſueto ſeſſionis loco conſervetur, poſtquam debitum ſuae Regiae Majeſtati Juramentum fidelitatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiterit, ſalvo manente libero in locis reſtitutis, uti antea viguit. Evangelicae Religionis exercitio, manente quoque libero Catholicae Religionis exercitio, in templo praeſertim Parochiali Veteris Civitatis Elbingenſis uti ante bellum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cunctae actiones adverſus illos, qui partes Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niſſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um Regum ac Reginae Sveciae quocunque modo ſecuti ſunt, aut ſecuti eſſe inſimulantur, cujuſque ſint ſtatus &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, five privati vixerint, vel officio publico functi, ac ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiis Sacrae Regiae Majeſtatis, Regnique Sueciae obſtricti fuerint, vel inſtituendae, vel inſtitutae, ceſſent, &amp; ſi quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentatae ſunt, tollantur, omnique careant executione in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum, nec quiſquam de iis, quae belli, Jnduciarumve tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore ex occaſione ejuſdem belli vel induciarum interceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cui quam respondere teneatur. Et ſi quid in contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m ſuſceptum, factumve eſt, aut reſcriptum vel decretum aliquod in abſentiâ partis obtentum, id omne ſit irritum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lliuſque valoris.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:13"/>
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>Si cui, aut quibus non placuerit in reſtitutis Civitatibus aut territoriis manere, ſed potiùs mutato domicilio ad ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ſe conferre, liberum ſit in ſpatio trium annorum, à data praeſentium numerando, ſua divendere, aliis locare, aut pro ſuo libitu diſtrahere ſine ullo impedimento aut onere, ſub quocunque pretextu imponendo, ſalvis antiquis Civitatum puribus ac conſuetudinibus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>Si qui exulum, qui extra Sueciam apud Polonos verſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nur, &amp; partes Sereniſſimorum Regum Poloniae ſecuti ſunt, in Patriam redire quacunque de cauſa voluerint, ſalvum quaerant conductum, quo impetrato, fruantur beneficio le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; ſtatutorum Regni Succiae.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>In locis quocunque tempore juxta praeſentia pacta reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endis, relinquantur bonâ fide omnia mobilia Eccleſiarum, quae in praeſens reperiuntur uti ſunt vaſa ac veſtes ſacrae, campanae, aliaque ad uſum Eccleſiaſticum ſervientia, tum libri Cancellariae, Privilegia &amp; acta publica. Si quae tamen temporum iniuria à milite ſunt direpta, aut aliorum negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiâ corrupta, ulterior in id inquiſitio non inſtituatur, nec quiſquam ad reſtitutionem teneatur. Tormenta item bellica &amp; Bombardae majores, quae tempore occupationis inventae fuerunt, &amp; adhuc in reſtituendis Civitatibus vel locis ſunt, celinquantur.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:14"/>
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>De iis, quae durante bello iure fiſci cuiquam ademta, &amp; vel Fiſco illata, vel aliis donata ſunt; ita convenit, ut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebilia ſive Regis &amp; Reip. ſive etiam privatorum ſint bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, quorum donationes utrinque factae ſunt, ſidonatarits jam tradita ſint antiquis poſſeſſoribus reſtituantur, ſi vero non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tradita, maneant penes Dominos: caſſantibus de caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro omuibus quaeſtionibus, actionibuſque ratione reditnum, five expublicis ſive privatis bonis perceptorum. Mobilium eriam donationes &amp; largitiones utrinque factae, ſi ante has inducias executioni non fuerint demandatae, irritae ſint, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditae vero poſſeſſoribus modernis relinquantur. Ceſſantibus quoque corum nomine omnibus actionibus, irritiſque obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatrunbus, quibus apochae authenticè ſive a Regum loca te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus, five ab officialibus Camerarum Regiarum, ſive &amp; ab ipſis donatariis, ſine frande datae, (dummodo de liſdem donationthus per authenticum inſtrumentum conſtet, ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enis factae) opponi poſſunt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="article">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>Commercia priſtina inter utrumque Regnum &amp; Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias ſubjectas reſtituantur, &amp; in veteri exercitio conſerven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, redeantque omnia in eumſtatum, in quo ante hoc bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liem fuerant, ab omnibus novitatibus, oneribuſque hoc bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo indictis vindicata.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:15"/>
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>Defluitatio mercium ex Mag. Duc. Lithv. nulla ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in flumine Dunâ impediatur: ſitque ea in dicto flumine vectigalium ratio in poſterum, quae fuit ante hoc bellum.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="article">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>Subditifugitivi Mag. Duc. Lith. &amp; Duc. Curland: quicunque in Livoniâ reperti fuerint, ſuis Dominis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur: quod vice verſade ſubditis fugitivis ex Livonia in Mag: Duc: Lith: &amp; Duc: Curland: fieri debet.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="article">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Exercitus omnes, (exceptis praeſidiariis) tempore ſupra definito ab utraque parte ex Provincia deducantur: &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Suecicus per mare, ſi tamen equitatui intra aſſignati temporis ſpatium traijciendo nav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m copia non ſuppetierit, liber illi &amp; innoxius tranſitus, quam breviſſime itinere, per terram in ditiones ipſorum ſine damno Jncolarum Regne Poloniae mediate vel immediate ſubjectorum, concedi debet, Quod itidem obſervetur, ſi aliqui pedites dicti Exercitus Suecici dimiſſi fuerint: Iuſtiria verè Prafectos indilatâ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ fide adminiſtretur damnum &amp; injuriam paſsis.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:16"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Injurias tam perſonales quam reales ſub haſce inducias incidentes una pars de alterâ non vindic abit, ſalva juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione ordinariâ cujuſque partis, ſed juſtitia ab officialibus &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>giſtratibus competenter requiratur, eademque indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata adminiſtretur, ſeverae poenae in violatores pacis, fide public â roboratae exerceantur: nullaque repreſſaliae aut ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſta, tâm terrâ quâm mari ratione cujuſcunque injuriae (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſi juſtitiae pluribus vicibus legitimè repetita non admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretur,) admittantur &amp; ſi qua ante hoc bellum ſive etiam durante b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llo conceſſa ſunt, caſſentur: ita tamen, ut quibus conceſſa ſunt, juſtitia adminiſtretur.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="article">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>Quod fi quid gravius incidert, quod violationem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum concernere videretur, dentur utrinque Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit qui loco aliquo ad fines Livoniae aſsignando conveniant, &amp; controverſias exortas ſopiant, decidant que.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="article">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>Pro majore ſecuritate, &amp; ne quicquam hiſce pactis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium durantibus induciis à quopiam committatur, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines Regni Poloniae, &amp; Mag. Duc. Lith. promitrant &amp; fide ſube<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt Regem Poloniae &amp; ejus fratres, corumque Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores ac Poſteros durantibus induciis, ex Regno Poloniae
<pb facs="tcp:18486:17"/>Magnoque Duc. Lith &amp; omnibus ejus ſubjectis Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis, at que ditionibus nihil molituros, multò minùs hoſtile quie quam tentaturos, adverſus Sereniſsimam Reginam, ejuſque Succeſſores, Reges, Regnumque Sueciae, ejuſque ſubjectas ditiones ac Provincias, Civitates, Caſtra, Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ac Territoria, &amp; ſi quicquam tentaverint, id impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, ac praevenire teneantur.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="article">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>Sacrae Regia Majeſtas &amp; Reſp. Polona adverſus Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſs. Reginam ejuſque Succeſſores, Reges, Regnum que Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae, ſubjectaſque ditiones, ac Provincias nullis navibus vel Claſſe Maritimâ utatur, vel aliis quibuſcunque auxilio ſubmittat durantibus Induciis. Et Dux in Pruſſiâ, Dux Churlandiae, &amp; ex ſtatibus Pruſſiae Regalis, Civitates ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeres caveant, ſe non permiſſures hoſtile quicquam ex por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tubus ſuis Reginae, Regnoque Sueciae, ſubjectiſque ditioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ac Provinciis, illatum iri directè vel indirectè</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:18"/>
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>Durantibus ac currentibus hiſce Jnduciis, agatur de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce perpetuâ loco ac tempore (interventu, Principum Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorum) de quibus inter partes, cura ac diligentia illuſtriſ. Duc: Churl, convenerit. Ita tamen ut ſi tractatus Pacis perpetuae ſemel aut iterum non ſucceſſerit, firmae nihil omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs &amp; inviolabiles maneant Jnduciae, uſque ad exitum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis praefinitum.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="article">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>Si qui Regum ac Principum Chriſtianorum hiſce pactis ex utraque parte includi voluerint, ſit ipſis ejus facultas: modo ſe ad iſta intra quinque abhinc menſes declaraverint.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="article">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Vt hiſce pactis firmius inſiſtatur, certeque conſtet, bona <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de ea ſervatum iri, hoc modo convenit, ut redditis utrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Procuratoriis Dominorum Commiſſariorum, pacta haec manu &amp; ſigillo eorundem roborentur &amp; invicem tradan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Tum ut Seren. Rex Poloniae ſecundum praeſcriptam for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adem quanto citius confirmet, &amp; antequam ullius
<pb facs="tcp:18486:19"/>loci fiat reſtitutio ſuam Confirmationem tradat. Deinde ut Sacra <hi>Sueciae</hi> ſolennni inſtrumento, illa nomine ſuo ac Regni <hi>Sueciae,</hi> per ſuperſcriptionem Dominorum Regni <hi>Sueciae</hi> Adminiſtratorum rata habeat. Et Reſpublica <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona</hi> eadem in Comitiis primo quoque Tempore celebrandis, ſolenniter approbet, &amp; confecto Jnſtrumento ratificet. Quae quidem Inſtrumenta ſolennia, ad formulam praeſcriptam, nulla voce aut ſyllaba mutata; per utriuſque Partis Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarios Deputatos quanto citius poterit, ad limites Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritoriales inter <hi>Elbingam</hi> &amp; <hi>Mariaeburgum,</hi> ſine ulla mora &amp; excuſatione reddi utrinque ac recipi debebunt. Ad eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem modum Sereniſſimus Elector <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> Dux in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> Dux <hi>Churlandiae,</hi> &amp; ex Ordinibus Regalis <hi>Pruſſiae</hi> Civitates Majores literas tuas Reverſales, quibus Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati. S. R. M. ac Regni <hi>Sueciae</hi> cavebitur, ant è reſtitutionem <hi>Elbingae</hi> &amp; <hi>Pillaviae</hi> tradant.</p>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Actum <hi>Stumiſdorffi</hi> 
                     <date>d. <hi>2. Septemb.</hi> Styl. vet. Anno ſalutis Milleſimo ſexcenteſimo trigeſimo quinto.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="ratification">
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:20"/>
               <p>Nos itaque Vladiſlaus IV. Rex Poloniae, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dux Lithvaniae, &amp;c. promittimus &amp; reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus nomine noſtro, Succeſſorum noſtrorum &amp; Reipub. Polonae, Nos ſingula &amp; univerſa Capita Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſupra ſcriptis inſerta &amp; comprehenſa bona &amp; Regia fide approbare, laudare &amp; ratihabere, ſicut hiſce appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus, laudamus &amp; ratihabemus: nec paſſuros a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratibus aut aliis ullo modo violari. In quorum majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fidem ac certitudinem hiſce manu noſtra ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, &amp; ſigillo Regni noſtri muniri juſsimus,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Datum in Caſtris ad Quidſinum <date>die <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Menſ. Septemb.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="treaty">
            <pb facs="tcp:18486:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> of the moſt High and mighty <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp; our Soveraigne <hi>Lord Vladiſlaus</hi> the fourth; by the grace of <hi>God King</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> Great Duke of <hi>Lettow,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo of the renowned Common-wealth of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> namely, <hi>Iames Zadzik</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Culm</hi> and <hi>Pomeſan,</hi> Lord <hi>Elect</hi> of <hi>Cracow,</hi> Duke of <hi>Severien, Provoſt</hi> Generall of <hi>Micheow,</hi> high <hi>Chancellour</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Poland: Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phael</hi> Count of <hi>Leſno,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Belxe,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Derpt</hi> &amp; <hi>Oberpol: Remigius Otok Zalesky; Referendary</hi> of the Kingdome: <hi>Iames Sobiezin,</hi> in <hi>Sobiesky Principall Carver</hi> of the Kingdome, Governour of <hi>Cranostaw</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worow:</hi> do hereby teſtifie and give notice to all whom it may concerne; That whereas there was a <hi>Peace</hi> concluded upon in the yeare 1629, betwixt the High and mighty Kings and Kingdomes of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and of <hi>Sweden:</hi> which intention, that in the meane time, by the intervening me diation of the High and mighty Princes their Majeſties of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> and of other Princes: either a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:18486:6"/>
               <hi>Peace,</hi> or a longer <hi>Truce,</hi> might be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon: the time and place for which <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> being to be aſſigned by his Highnes the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> (one of the <hi>Mediators</hi>) with the good liking of both the Parties. Now, whereas by his ſaid <hi>Highneſſe</hi> his <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours;</hi> the Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> Marqueſſe of Brandenburg; and the illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and magnificent <hi>Andrew á Creutzen,</hi> of the Privy Councell for the Dukedome of Pruſſia, Regent, and Governour of the County: <hi>Iohn George á Sauken,</hi> Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, Regent and Chancellour: <hi>Bernard á Conigseck</hi> Counſellour: <hi>George á Rausckeu,</hi> Councellour of the Iuſtice-ſeat within the Verge of the Court: and <hi>Peter Bergkman</hi> Councellour of the Privy Councell: Wee (the ſaid Commiſſioners) having beene invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Strumſdorff; and there having met with the Illuſtrious Commiſſioners of the Queens Majeſtie and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> Namely, the Lord <hi>Peter Brabe</hi> Count of <hi>Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningsburgh,</hi> Baron of <hi>Ridholme</hi> and <hi>Lindholm,</hi> of the Privy Councell of the Kingdome, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>High dutch</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, retains the Latine word <hi>legife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro:</hi> to that it ſeemes to be the very Swediſh word for that <hi>Office.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>Weſtmannia,</hi> of the <hi>Mountaine,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:18486:7"/>
               <hi>Dale-Carls: Herman Wrangeln;</hi> of Privy Councell of the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden; Felt-Marſhall</hi> of the Army, <hi>Hereaitary</hi> in <hi>Lerge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm, Sko-Cloſher,</hi> Knight: <hi>Acatius</hi> ſonne of <hi>Axel,</hi> Councellour of the Kingdome of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and Legifer of <hi>Nericia,</hi> Hereditary of <hi>Coxholm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iohn Oxenſtierna</hi> ſonne of <hi>Axel,</hi> of the Privy Councell to the Queens Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, Baron of <hi>Kimoth,</hi> Lord of <hi>Fiholm</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doen:</hi> and <hi>Iohn Nicodemi,</hi> Principall <hi>Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>State</hi> unto her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſary-Generall</hi> of the Army in <hi>Pruſsia: Wee the ſaid Commiſsiones for both Parties being thus aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;</hi> and upon the mediation eſpecially of the High and mighty Prince CHARLES King of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c. Defender of the Faith, preſented by Sir <hi>George Douglaſſe</hi> Knight, <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> for his ſaid ſacred <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty:</hi> and by the meadiation of the High and mighty Prince <hi>Lewis the thirteenth,</hi> the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Navarre:</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Illuſtrious <hi>Claudé de Meſmes,</hi> Knight, Lord of <hi>Avaux;</hi> Extraordinary <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour</hi> for his ſacred <hi>Maieſtie</hi> into theſe <hi>Northern Kingdomes:</hi> as alſo (<hi>upon the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:18486:8"/>of the High &amp; mighty Lords the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Vnited Provinces;</hi> preſented by their <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> the Illuſtrious &amp; magnificent <hi>Roch Vanden Honaert,</hi> firſt Counſellor in the great Court of <hi>Holland, Zeland,</hi> and <hi>West-frizeland: Andrew Bicker,</hi> Burgomaſter of <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> and <hi>Ioachim Andrea,</hi> Counſellor in the higheſt Court of <hi>Frizeland:</hi> having entred into the ſaid <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and for a long-while, many wayes too and againe conſulted thereupon; to this iſſue, at length; (the divine goodneſſe graciouſly therein fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring us, and the right Honourable Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours aforeſaid, taking indefatigable pains in it) we brought the whole buſineſſe; as that we fully agreed, determined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded upon the <hi>Peace,</hi> with the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> of her <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and of the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in manner and forme following.</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:9"/>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>LEt the <hi>Peace,</hi> betwixt the High and Mighty Prince <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>Poland,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lettow,</hi> &amp;c. our gratious Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; his Majeſties ſucceſſors, Kings of <hi>Poland,</hi> nd great Dukes of <hi>Lettow;</hi> as alſo the Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> on the one party, and the High and mighty Princeſſe and Lady, the Lady <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> deſigned Queene of the <hi>Swedens, Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> great Princeſſe of <hi>Finland,</hi> &amp;c. Her <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſucceſſors Kings of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as alſo the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> on the other party: be <hi>continued</hi> from this day forward, for XXVI. yeares to come; to be accounted from the date of theſe preſents, untill the firſt of <hi>Iuly,</hi> (old ſtyle) in the yeare of our Lord 1661.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Let there be an utter forgetfulneſſe of all fore-paſſed matters, on both ſides. And, in the firſt place, let his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, and the Kings his ſucceſſors, as alſo the whole Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and great Dukes of <hi>Lettow:</hi> abſtaine during the whole time of the ſaid <hi>Peace,</hi> from all manner of hoſtility againſt the Queene and kingdome of <hi>Sweden;</hi> and the Countries, Caſtles, Cities and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, mediately or immediately belonging unto them: yea, and neither by themſelves or any others, Let them complot, attempt, or cauſe to be attempted any thing, in derogation or infringement of theſe Articles. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Let her Majeſtie the Queen, with the Kings her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, &amp; Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> forbeare for all the time of this <hi>Peace,</hi> from all actions of hoſtility againſt the King and Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow;</hi> and againſt all the Countries, Caſtles, Cities, and Dominions, either mediately or immediately ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; yea, and neither by themſelves or by any others, let them complot, attempt, or cauſe to be attempted, any thing in derogation or infringement of theſe Articles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:10"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>Let her Majeſtie and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> reſtore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Majeſty and Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> all that part of <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> as yet in their poſſeſſion. Yet ſo, that the <hi>Pillaw</hi> be immediately reſtored unto the Elector of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> Duke in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> to be holden by the ſame right, as before this warre he ſtill enjoyed it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>But in reſtoring of places; let this one thing be obſerved, that upon the <hi>Ratification</hi> (of this Peace) by the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> caution being alſo laid in by the <hi>States,</hi> as alſo by certaine <hi>Poliſh Commiſſioners</hi> by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> ſent from the Common-wealth unto the Kings preſence, with aſſurance of delivering the Ratification <hi>(of this preſent Peace)</hi> of the Common-wealth ſo ſoone as conveniently may be: <hi>Marienburg</hi> with the * greater <hi>Jland,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The</hi> Goſie Werder <hi>by</hi> Marienburg.</note> 
                     <hi>Stum, Brunsberg,</hi> and <hi>Tolkemit,</hi> with their Territories, the <hi>(Swediſh)</hi> garriſons being firſt drawn our; be rendred up into the hands of the Commiſſioners of the King and Kingdome of <hi>Poland.</hi> But as for <hi>Haubt</hi> and <hi>Junckertreil,</hi> let them be demoliſhed even with the ground, in preſence of certaine Deputies for both parties; the lands and goods belonging to them being reſtored to their owners. Let the Armies alſo on both ſides be drawne off, within that time, in the ſame order and manner as ſhall be agreed upon betwixt both the Generals. As for <hi>Elbing</hi> and the territory antiently belonging to it, with the <hi>leſſer Iland,</hi> and the Fortifications therein erected; as alſo the <hi>Pillaw,</hi> with that part of <hi>Neringen</hi> which belongs unto it; her Majeſty and the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden</hi> may ſo long keepe poſſeſſion of them, untill the foreſaid <hi>Ratification</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Poland</hi> be obtained. Which being tendred, her Majeſty is to deliver up theſe places alſo within 14. dayes, and to draw out all her Garriſons, without hurt-doing to the inhabitants. This being therewithall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that all the Fortifications erected about <hi>Elbing,</hi> bee left in the ſame ſtate they now are, and under the ſame government as before theſe warres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:11"/>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <p>After the reſtitution of all places, let the tributes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the ſame ſtate and right they were in before theſe warres: equality being in every thing obſerved, as before times.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>All <hi>Acts, Iudgements,</hi> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> upon what inſtance or ſentence ſoever paſſed: all <hi>Writings, Contracts, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions,</hi> and all <hi>Actions,</hi> which are no way derogatory unto the publike State, as it was before theſe warres, or which are not by expreſſe words excepted in this preſent <hi>Agreement;</hi> however concluded, either in the time of <hi>Warre</hi> or <hi>Truce,</hi> by the authority of the Magiſtrate and judicially; or otherwiſe beſides the <hi>formalityes</hi> of the <hi>Law:</hi> let them remaine in as full ſtrength as if all had been done when things were in their former condition; and as if no alteration, either in the <hi>Government</hi> or of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</hi> had happened.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>So much as either party had in their poſſeſſion in the Country of <hi>Leifland,</hi> during the time of the laſt ſixe years Peace: let them ſtill keepe poſſeſſion of for all the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixe yeares following.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:12"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>Whatſoever Cities or Territories, with their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Commons, and Inhabitants, and Subjects in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which the King and State of <hi>Poland</hi> have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received under their protection; let them henceforth grant free pardon unto; yea and afford favour, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them with the ſame clemency and grace, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and let all and every of them enjoy the ſame poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Rights, Priviledges and Cuſtomes, (as well gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and common as ſpeciall) without exception, which before the beginning of theſe warres they have enjoyed. And eſpecially let the City of <hi>Elbing</hi> be conſerved in the right and uſage of the <hi>Seale</hi> of the Lands of <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and in the accuſtomed Seate of Iuſtice: it having, in the firſt place, taken the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Fidelity</hi> to the Kings Majeſty: the exerciſe of the <hi>Evangelicall religion</hi> being left free in the reſtored places, as it heretofore hath flouriſhed: yea and the exerciſe of the <hi>Catholike</hi> religion, being left free alſo; eſpecially in the Pariſh Church of the old towne of <hi>Elbing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> as it was before theſe warres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>All <hi>Actions</hi> againſt thoſe perſons, which in any kinde have taken part with their Majeſties the King and Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or that are accuſed to have ſided with them; of what condition or degree ſoever they be, whether they have lived as private men, or have borne any office, or any way beene employed in the ſervice of their ſaid ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſties, or of the kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whether the ſaid Actions be already commenced or intended ſo to be, let them be let fall preſently: and if any be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſſed, let them inſtantly be diſanulled and debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all further execution for ever. Nor let any man be thereby engaged to put in Anſwer to any adverſary, upon ſuch things as have beene done in the time either of Warre or Peace; which have fallen out upon occaſion of the ſaid Warre or Peace. And if that contrary hereunto, any ſuit already be commenced or adjudged, or any Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or Order of Law in the abſence of the party be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, let it wholly be made word &amp; of no value.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:13"/>
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>If any perſon or perſons be not willing longer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in the reſtored Cities or Territories; but rather to change his dwelling and remove unto another place: let him have free leave within three yeares from the date of theſe preſents, either to ſell outright, let to farme to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or otherwiſe at his or their pleaſures to diſpoſe of his eſtate, without any hindrance or taxation upon any pretence to be impoſed on them: the ancient Rights and Cuſtomes of the Citizens, being ſtill preſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>Whatſoever Exiles now out of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving among the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Nation, that have ſometimes followed the party of their Majeſties the Kings of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> be willing, upon any occaſion, to returne into their owne Country: let them deſire <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Safe-conduct;</hi> which being obtained, they may freely enjoy the benefit of the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>In ſuch places, as are at any time by vertue of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Agreement</hi> to be reſtored; let all the <hi>Church-move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables</hi> at this time found in them, bee faithfully left unto them. That is to ſay, ſacred Veſſels and Veſtments, Bels, and other Ornaments ſerving for the Church: as alſo the Books of their <hi>Courts of Chancerie,</hi> their <hi>Patents</hi> and <hi>Publick Acts.</hi> But if any of them through the injury of the times have beene pillaged by the Souldiours, or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers negligence have beene ſpoyled: let no further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry be made into it, nor any man obliged to reſtitution. As for thoſe peeces of Canon and great Ordnance, which at the time of the taking were found, and are yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in any of the Cities or places that are to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, let them be there left unto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:14"/>
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>As concerning thoſe goods, which in the time of theſe warres have be the Law of <hi>Atteinder</hi> been taken from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon; or which have been <hi>confiſcated,</hi> or beſtowed upon other: it is thus agreed upon That is to ſay, that the <hi>Immoveable goods</hi> belonging either to the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> or elſe unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> private perſon, which are actually already given away, on either ſide: if ſo be they be already deliver dup, into the poſſeſſion of theſe to whom they were given: let t em be again reſtored to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> former ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but if poſſeſſion be not already given of them, let them ſtill remayne unto their owners: all <hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> in regard of any <hi>Rents</hi> received for them, either of the goods of private men, or of the <hi>State;</hi> from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth for ever ceaſing. As for thoſe Grants or Gifts of <hi>moveable</hi> goods, made on either ſide; if actuall poſſeſſion have not thereupon beene delivered, let the grants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come void: but as for ſuch as have been delivered, let them be ſtill left unto the preſent poſſeſſors. All <hi>Actions,</hi> alſo, in their names ceaſing, and all <hi>Bonds</hi> becomming voide; which by ſuch <hi>Acquitances</hi> may be diſcharged, as either by the Kings <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> or by the <hi>Officers</hi> of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Chamber,</hi> or by the <hi>Donors</hi> themſelues, have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentically and without fraude beene given; provided, that by ſome authentick writing of payment heretofore made; there may be a <hi>Conſtat</hi> of thoſe <hi>Donations.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="article">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>Let the ancient Commerce betwixt either Kingdome and the ſubject <hi>Provinces,</hi> be againe reſtored; and from hence in their ancient Freedome conſerved: and let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing returne into the ſame eſtate, wher in they were before theſe warres: and theſe diſcharged from all ſuch novell Impoſitions and Taxations, as have theſe warres beene laid upon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:15"/>
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>Let the paſſing of Merchandiſes out of the great Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> by the River <hi>Duna,</hi> by no means be no longer hindred: yea, and let the ſame rates of <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> hereafter be upon that River, which were before the Warres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="article">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>Let all ſuch Fugitive Subjects of the great Duke dome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> and Dukedome of <hi>Curland,</hi> as are found in <hi>Liefland,</hi> be retured to their owne Lords: which, on the other ſide, ought alſo to be done, with the Fugitive Subjects out of <hi>Liefland,</hi> into the great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> and the Duchy of <hi>Curland.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="article">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>Let all the <hi>Armies</hi> (excepting the <hi>Garriſons</hi>) be on both ſides drawne out of the Country within the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army to paſſe away by Sea. But in caſe they ſhould not be furniſht of ſhipping enow by the time appointed, for wafting over of the <hi>Horſe;</hi> that then the ſaid <hi>Horſe-forces</hi> ſhould have free paſſage and unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, to march over-land, the neereſt way into their own Dominions: ſo be it were without wrong-doing unto ſuch Inhabitants, as either mediately or immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be Subjects to the Crowne of <hi>Poland.</hi> Which conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is alſo to be obſerved, if any <hi>Foot</hi> of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army ſhall be <hi>caſhiered:</hi> preſent Iuſtice being <hi>bona fide</hi> to be adminiſtred by the <hi>Commanders,</hi> unto ſuch as ſuffer loſſe, or receive injury by them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:16"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>Injuries, whether <hi>perſonall</hi> or <hi>reall,</hi> falling out within the time of this <hi>Peace;</hi> ſhall not one part revenge upon another; the ordinary <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> of each Party being preſerved: but Iuſtice ſhall orderly be demanded of the Officers and the Magiſtrates: which without delaying, let it forthwith be adminiſtred. Let ſevere puniſhment be inflicted upon the violaters of this <hi>Peace:</hi> which by the publick Faith and Honour is now confirmed. And let no <hi>Repriſals</hi> or <hi>Arreſts,</hi> either by Sea or Land be allowed; done upon pretence of any injury whatſoever; unleſſe that Iuſtice hath often been demanded, and not adminiſtred. And <hi>Licence</hi> for making ſuch <hi>Repriſals</hi> or <hi>Arreſts,</hi> have during theſe warres been made out, let them be held for cancelled: with this <hi>proviſo,</hi> that Inſtice be forthwith done, unto whom ſuch <hi>Licences</hi> have been granted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="article">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>But if any waighty occaſion ſhall fall out, which may ſeeme to concerne the breaking of theſe <hi>Articles;</hi> let <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> be on either ſide appointed: who meeting in ſome deſigned place upon the Frontiers of <hi>Lieſtland</hi> may decide the late riſen Controverſies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="article">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>For the more ſecurity, and that nothing contrary unto this <hi>Agreement,</hi> may during this <hi>Peace</hi> by any man be committed; let the <hi>States</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> paſſe their promiſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage their Faiths for the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> his <hi>Brothers,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors;</hi> that for all the time of this <hi>Peace,</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:18486:17"/>ſhall not complot to do any thing, either out of <hi>Poland</hi> and the great Dukedome of <hi>Lettow,</hi> nor out of any of the Countries and Dominions ſubject unto them: much leſſe that they ſhall actually attempt any action of hoſtility, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Queens Majeſty or the Kings her Succeſſours, and the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden;</hi> or againſt the Dominions, Countries, Cities, Caſtles, Forts and Territories object unto them: yea, and in caſe the King or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Brethren, &amp;c. ſhould attempt any ſuch matter; let the <hi>States</hi> be hereby engaged, to hinder and to prevent it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="article">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>The Kings ſacred Majeſty and Common-wealth of <hi>Poland,</hi> ſhall imploy no ſhipping or Sea-fleet, againſt her Majeſty the Queen, and the Kings her Succeſſours, and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden;</hi> or againſt their Dominions and Subject Provinces: nor ſhall ſend ſuch aide un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others againſt them, during all the time of the ſaid <hi>Peace.</hi> Alſo the Duke in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg.</hi>
                     </note> the Duke of <hi>Curland,</hi> and of the <hi>States</hi> of that part of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> belonging to the <hi>King,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Of</hi> Poland.</note> let the greater Cities put in caution, that they will not ſuffer any hoſtility, either directly or indirectly, out of their <hi>Ports</hi> to be ſent againſt the Queene &amp; Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the Dominions and Countries to them ſubject.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18486:18"/>
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>During this preſent Peace, and before it be expired, let another Treaty be propounded for the perpetuating of it in ſuch place and time, (by the intervention of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Mediators) as ſhall be agreed upon by both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, brought to it by the care and diligence of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Duke of <hi>Curland.</hi> Yet ſo, that if this Treaty for a <hi>perpetuall Peace,</hi> ſucceeds not at the firſt or ſecond time, yet let the preſent Truce remaine firme and inviolable, unto the full terme prefixed in this Agreement.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="article">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>If any Kings or Princes <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> be deſirous to be on either Party included within this <hi>Peace,</hi> let them hereby have liberty to doe it: upon condition, that they declare themſelves for it within five moneths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="article">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>To the intent this preſent agreement may the more firmely be relyed upon, and that it may aſſuredly be made appeare, it ſhall <hi>bona fide</hi> be obſerved; it is in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner concluded upon. That the Exceptions of the Lords Commiſſioners being on both ſides returned backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, let theſe Articles be confirmed with their hands and Seales, and mutually be delivered. Then, that his Majeſty the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> may according to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent preſcript forme, confirme it with all ſpeed poſſible, and deliver up that his Confirmation, before any place be reſtored. Then, that her ſacred Majeſty of <hi>Sweden</hi> may alſo ratifie it by a ſolemne Inſtrument, in her own name and the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> by the Subſcriptions of of the Lords <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> And that the State of <hi>Poland,</hi> in their Parliament
<pb facs="tcp:18486:19"/>with all ſpeed to be convoked, may ſolemnly approve of it, and in an Inſtrument drawne to that purpoſe ratifie it. Which ſaid ſolemne Inſtruments, in this preſent forme preſcribed (not ſo mvch as one word or ſyllable being altered) ſhall with all ſpeed poſſible, by the deputed Commiſſioners on both ſides, without any delay or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, upon the Frontiers betwixt <hi>Elbing</hi> and <hi>Marien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> be mutually delivered and received. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, his Highneſſe the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and Duke in. <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Curland,</hi> and of the States of <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> on the Kings ſide, the greater Cities, ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their <hi>Letters Reverſalls,</hi> in which Caution ſhall be layd in, for the ſecurity of her Majeſty and the kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> before ſuch time as <hi>Elbing</hi> and the <hi>Pillaw</hi> be reſtored.</p>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dated at</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">In Pruſſia</note> Stumſdorff <hi>the ſecond of</hi> 
                     <date>September, <hi>old ſtile: in the yeete of our Lord,</hi> 1635.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="ratification">
               <pb facs="tcp:18486:20"/>
               <p>VVE therefore, <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>Poland,</hi> great Duke of <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tow,</hi> &amp;c. doe hereby promiſe and undertake in our own name, and of our Succeſſors and State of <hi>Poland,</hi> That all and every one of theſe Articles in the above written Agreement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and comprehended, Wee with a good and Kingly fidelity, profeſſe to approove, commend and ratifie: like as hereby we actually doe approve, commend, and ratifie them: nor will we ſuffer them by our owne or any other people, to be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. For the better credit and aſſurance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, We have ſigned to them with our owne hand, and have commanded them to be firmed with the Broad Seale of our Kingdome.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given in our Campe at <hi>Quidſin</hi> by <hi>Marienwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>Pruſſia.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> of September.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
L. S.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
